<div1 id="copyright"><head>Copyright Notice</head>
<!-- $Id: copyright.xml,v 1.5 2009/05/31 02:10:44 rminer Exp $ -->

<p class="copyright"><a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#Copyright">Copyright</a> &copy; 2009 <a href="http://www.w3.org/"><acronym title="World Wide Web Consortium">W3C</acronym></a><sup>&reg;</sup> (<a href="http://www.csail.mit.edu/"><acronym title="Massachusetts Institute of Technology">MIT</acronym></a>, <a href="http://www.ercim.org/"><acronym title="European Research Consortium for Informatics and Mathematics">ERCIM</acronym></a>, <a href="http://www.keio.ac.jp/">Keio</a>), All Rights Reserved. W3C <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#Legal_Disclaimer">liability</a>, <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#W3C_Trademarks">trademark</a> and <a href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/copyright-documents">document use</a> rules apply.</p>

<p>Documents on the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/">W3C</loc> site are
provided by the copyright holders under the following license. By
obtaining, using and/or copying this document, or the W3C document from
which this statement is linked, you agree that you have read, understood,
and will comply with the following terms and conditions:</p>

<p>Permission to use, copy, and distribute the contents of this document,
or the W3C document from which this statement is linked, in any medium for
any purpose and without fee or royalty is hereby granted, provided that you
include the following on <emph>ALL</emph> copies of the document, or
portions thereof, that you use:

<olist>
<item><p>A link or URI to the original W3C document.</p></item>

<item><p>The pre-existing copyright notice of the original author, if it
doesn't exist, a notice of the form: <quote><a rel="Copyright"
href="/Consortium/Legal/ipr-notice#Copyright">Copyright</a> &#xa9; 1994-2003
<a href="/"><acronym
title="World Wide Web Consortium">W3C</acronym></a><sup>&#xae;</sup> (<a
href="http://www.lcs.mit.edu/"><acronym
title="Massachusetts Institute of Technology">MIT</acronym></a>, <a
href="http://www.ercim.org/"><acronym
title="European Research Consortium for Informatics and
Mathematics">ERCIM</acronym></a>, <a
href="http://www.keio.ac.jp/">Keio</a>), All Rights Reserved.</quote>.</p></item>

<item><p><emph>If it exists</emph>, the STATUS of the W3C document.</p></item>
</olist></p>

<p>When space permits, inclusion of the full text of this <emph
role='important'>NOTICE</emph> should be provided. In addition, credit
shall be attributed to the copyright holders for any software, documents,
or other items or products that you create pursuant to the implementation
of the contents of this document, or any portion thereof.</p>

<p>No right to create modifications or derivatives is granted pursuant to
this license.</p>

<p role='important'>THIS DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED <quote>AS IS</quote>, AND
COPYRIGHT HOLDERS MAKE NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, NON-INFRINGEMENT, OR TITLE; THAT THE
CONTENTS OF THE DOCUMENT ARE SUITABLE FOR ANY PURPOSE; NOR THAT THE
IMPLEMENTATION OF SUCH CONTENTS WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY THIRD PARTY PATENTS,
COPYRIGHTS, TRADEMARKS OR OTHER RIGHTS.</p>

<p role='important'>COPYRIGHT HOLDERS WILL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT,
INDIRECT, SPECIAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THE
DOCUMENT OR THE PERFORMANCE OR IMPLEMENTATION OF THE CONTENTS THEREOF.</p>

<p>The name and trademarks of copyright holders may NOT be used in
advertising or publicity pertaining to this document or its contents
without specific, written prior permission. Title to copyright in this
document will at all times remain with copyright holders.</p>
</div1>
