<inform-div1 id="glossary" role="appendixh" ><head>Glossary</head>
<!-- $Id: glossary.xml,v 1.30 2009/11/08 15:58:28 dcarlis Exp $ -->

<p>Several of the following definitions of terms have been borrowed or
modified from similar definitions in documents originating from W3C or
standards organizations. See the individual definitions for more
information.</p>

<glist>
<gitem>
<label id="dt-argument">Argument</label>
<def><p>A child of a presentation layout schema. That is, <quote>A is an
argument of B</quote> means <quote>A is a child of B and B is a
presentation layout schema</quote>. Thus, token elements have no arguments,
even if they have children (which can only be 
<el>malignmark</el>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-attribute">Attribute</label>
<def><p>A parameter used to specify some property of an SGML or XML element
type. It is defined in terms of an attribute name, attribute type, and a
default value.  A value may be specified for it on a start-tag for that
element type.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-axis">Axis</label>
<def><p>The axis is an imaginary alignment line upon which a fraction line
is centered. Often, operators as well as characters that can stretch, such
as parentheses, brackets, braces, summation signs etc., are centered on
the axis, and are symmetric with respect to it.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-baseline">Baseline</label>
<def><p>The baseline is an imaginary alignment line upon which a glyph
without a descender rests.  The baseline is an intrinsic property of the
glyph (namely a horizontal line). Often baselines are aligned (joined)
during typesetting.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-blackbox">Black box</label>
<def><p>The bounding box of the actual size taken up by the viewable
portion (ink) of a glyph or expression.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-boundingbox">Bounding box</label>
<def><p>The rectangular box of smallest size, taking into account the
constraints on boxes allowed in a particular context, which contains some
specific part of a rendered display.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-box">Box</label>
<def><p>A rectangular plane area considered to contain a character or
further sub-boxes, used in discussions of rendering for display. It is
usually considered to have a baseline, height, depth and width.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-css">Cascading Style Sheets (CSS)</label>
<def><p>A language that allows authors and readers to attach style
(e.g. fonts, colors and spacing) to HTML and XML documents.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-character">Character</label>
<def><p>A member of a set of identifiers used for the organization, control
or representation of text. ISO/IEC Standard 10646-1:1993 uses the word
<quote>data</quote> here instead of <quote>text</quote>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-cdata">Character data (<kw>CDATA</kw>)</label>
<def><p>A data type in SGML and XML for raw data that does not include
markup or entity references. Attributes of type <kw>CDATA</kw> may contain
entity references. These are expanded by an XML processor before the
attribute value is processed as <kw>CDATA</kw>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-char-depth">Character or expression depth</label>
<def><p>Distance between the baseline and bottom edge of the character
glyph or expression. Also known as the descent.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-char-height">Character or expression height</label>
<def><p>Distance between the baseline and top edge of the character glyph
or expression. Also known as the ascent.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-char-width">Character or expression width</label>
<def><p>Horizontal distance taken by the character glyph as indicated in
the font metrics, or the total width of an expression.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-condition">Condition</label>
<def><p>A MathML content element used to place a mathematical condition on
one or more variables.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-contained">Contained (element A is contained in element B)</label>
<def><p>A is part of B's content.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-container">Container (Constructor)</label>
<def><p>A non-empty Content MathML element that is used to construct a
mathematical object such as a number, set, or list.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-content-elements">Content elements</label>
<def><p>MathML elements that explicitly specify the mathematical meaning
of a portion of a MathML expression (defined in <specref ref="contm"/>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-content-token-element">Content token element</label>
<def><p>Content element having only <kw>PCDATA</kw>, <el>sep</el>
and presentation expressions as content. Represents either an identifier
(<el>ci</el>) or a number (<el>cn</el>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-context">Context (of a given MathML expression)</label>
<def><p>Information provided during the rendering of some MathML data to
the rendering process for the given MathML expression; especially
information about the MathML markup surrounding the expression.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-declaration">Declaration</label>
<def><p>An instance of the declare element.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-depth">Depth</label>
<def><p>(of a box) The distance from the baseline of the box to the bottom
edge of the box.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-direct-sub-expression">Direct sub-expression
(of a MathML expression <quote>E</quote>)</label>
<def><p>A sub-expression directly contained in E.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-directly-contained">Directly contained
(element A in element B)</label>
<def><p>A is a child of B (as defined in XML), in other words
A is contained in B, but not in any element that is itself contained in
B.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-dom">Document Object Model</label>
<def><p>A model in which the document or Web page is treated as an object
repository. This model is developed by the DOM Working Group (DOM) of the
W3C.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-dsssl">Document Style Semantics and Specification Language (DSSSL)</label>
<def><p>A method of specifying the formatting and transformation of
SGML documents. ISO International Standard 10179:1996.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-dtd">Document Type Definition (DTD)</label>
<def><p>In SGML or XML, a DTD is a formal definition of the elements and
the relationship among the data elements (the structure) for a particular
type of document.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-em">Em</label>
<def><p>A font-relative measure encoded by the font. Before electronic
typesetting, an <attval>em</attval> was the width of an
<quote>M</quote> in the font. In modern usage, an <attval>em</attval>
is either specified by the designer of the font or is taken to be the
height (point size) of the font. Em's are typically used for font-relative
horizontal sizes.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-ex">Ex</label>
<def><p>A font-relative measure that is the height of an <quote>x</quote>
in the font.  <attval>ex</attval>s are typically used for
font-relative vertical sizes.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-height">Height</label>
<def><p>(of a box) The distance from the baseline of the box to the top
edge of the box.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-inferred-mrow">Inferred <el>mrow</el></label>
<def><p>An <el>mrow</el> element that is
<quote>inferred</quote> around the contents of certain layout schemata when
they have other than exactly one argument. Defined precisely in <specref
ref="presm_summary"/></p>
</def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-embedded-object">Embedded object</label>
<def><p>Embedded objects such as Java applets, Microsoft Component Object
Model (COM) objects (e.g. ActiveX Controls and ActiveX Document
embeddings), and plug-ins that reside in an HTML document.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-embellished-operator">Embellished operator</label>
<def><p>An operator, including any <quote>embellishment</quote> it may
have, such as superscripts or style information. The
<quote>embellishment</quote> is represented by a layout schema that
contains the operator itself.
Defined precisely in <specref ref="presm_mo"/>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-entity-reference">Entity reference</label>
<def><p>A sequence of ASCII characters of the form <kw
role="entity">name</kw> representing some other data, typically a
non-ASCII character, a sequence of characters, or an external source of
data, e.g. a file containing a set of standard entity definitions such as
ISO Latin 1.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-xml">Extensible Markup Language (XML)</label>
<def><p>A simple dialect of SGML intended to enable generic SGML to be
served, received, and processed on the Web.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-fences">Fences</label>
<def><p>In typesetting, bracketing tokens like parentheses, braces, and
brackets, which usually appear in matched pairs.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-font">Font</label>
<def><p>A particular collection of glyphs of a typeface of a given size,
weight and style, for example <quote>Times Roman Bold 12 point</quote>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-glyph">Glyph</label>
<def><p>The actual shape (bit pattern, outline) of a character.
ISO/IEC Standard 9541-1:1991 defines a glyph as a recognizable abstract 
graphic symbol that is independent of any specific design.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-indirectly-contained">Indirectly contained</label>
<def><p>A is contained in B, but not directly contained in B.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-mathml-instance">Instance of MathML</label>
<def><p>A single instance of the top level element of MathML, and/or a
single instance of embedded MathML in some other data format.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-inverse-function">Inverse function</label>
<def><p>A mathematical function that, when composed with the original
function acts like an identity function.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-lambda-exp">Lambda expression</label>
<def><p>A mathematical expression used to define a function in terms of
variables and an expression in those variables.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-layout-schema">Layout schema (plural: schemata)</label>
<def><p>A presentation element defined in chapter 3, other than the token
elements and empty elements defined there (i.e. not the elements defined in
<specref ref="presm_tokel"/> and <specref ref="presm_malign"/>, or the
empty elements <el>none</el> and
<el>mprescripts</el> defined in <specref ref="presm_mmultiscripts"/>).
The layout schemata are never empty elements (though their content may
contain nothing in some cases), are always expressions, and all allow any
MathML expressions as arguments (except for requirements on argument count,
and the requirement for a certain empty element in <el>mmultiscripts</el>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-mathml">Mathematical Markup Language (MathML)</label>
<def><p>The markup language specified in this document for describing
the structure of mathematical expressions, together with a mathematical
context.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-mathml-element">MathML element</label>
<def><p>An XML element that forms part of the logical structure of a
MathML document.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-mathml-exp">MathML expression (within some valid MathML
data)</label>
<def><p>A single instance of a presentation element, except for the empty
elements <el>none</el> or
<el>mprescripts</el>, or an instance of <el>malignmark</el> within a token element (defined below);
or a single instance of certain of the content elements
(see <specref ref="contm"/> for a precise definition of which ones).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-mime">Multi-purpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME)</label>
<def><p>A set of specifications that offers a way to interchange text in
languages with different character sets, and multimedia content among many
different computer systems that use Internet mail standards.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-operator-content">Operator, content element</label>
<def><p>A mathematical object that is applied to arguments using the 
<el>apply</el> element.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-operator">Operator, an <el>mo</el>
element</label>
<def><p>Used to represent ordinary operators, fences, separators in MathML
presentation. (The token element <el>mo</el> is defined in
<specref ref="presm_mo"/>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-openmath">OpenMath</label>
<def><p>A general representation language for communicating mathematical
objects between application programs.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-pcdata">Parsed character data (<kw>PCDATA</kw>)</label>
<def><p>An SGML/XML data type for raw data occurring in a context where
text is parsed and markup (for instance entity references and element
start/end tags) is recognized.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-pt">Point</label>
<def><p>Point is often abbreviated <quote>pt</quote>. The value of 1 pt 
is approximately 1/72 inch. Points are typically used to specify
absolute sizes for font-related objects.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>

<label id="dt-pres-elements">Presentation elements</label>
<def><p>MathML tags and entities intended to express the syntactic
structure of mathematical notation (defined in <specref ref="presm"/>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-pres-layout-schema">Presentation layout schema</label>
<def><p>A presentation element that can have other MathML elements as
content.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-pres-token-element">Presentation token element</label>
<def><p>A presentation element that can contain only parsed character data
or the <el>malignmark</el> element.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-qualifier">Qualifier</label>
<def><p>A MathML content element that is used to specify the value of a
specific named parameter in the application of selected pre-defined
functions.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-relation">Relation</label>
<def><p>A MathML content element used to construct expressions such as
<var>a</var> &lt; <var>b</var>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-render">Render</label>
<def><p>Faithfully translate into application-specific form allowing native
application operations to be performed.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-schema">Schema</label>
<def><p>Schema (plural: schemata or schemata). See <quote>presentation layout
schema</quote>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-declaration-scope">Scope of a declaration</label>
<def><p>The portion of a MathML document in which a particular
definition is active.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-selected-sub-exp">Selected sub-expression
(of an <el>maction</el> element)</label>
<def><p>The argument of an <el>maction</el> element (a
layout schema defined in <specref ref="presm_enliven"/>) that is (at any
given time) <quote>selected</quote> within the viewing state of a MathML
renderer, or by the <att>selection</att> attribute when the
element exists only in MathML data. Defined precisely in the aforementioned
section.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-spacelike">Space-like (MathML expression)</label>
<def><p>A MathML expression that is ignored by the suggested rendering
rules for MathML presentation elements when they determine operator forms
and effective operator rendering attributes based on operator positions in
<el>mrow</el> elements. Defined precisely in <specref
ref="presm_mspace"/>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-sgml">Standard Generalized Markup Language (SGML)</label>
<def><p>An ISO standard (ISO 8879:1986) that provides a formal
mechanism for the definition of document structure via DTDs (Document
Type Definitions), and a notation for the markup of document instances
conforming to a DTD.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-sub-exp">Sub-expression (of a MathML expression
<quote>E</quote>)</label>
<def><p>A MathML expression contained (directly or indirectly) in the
content of E.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-suggested-rendering-rules">Suggested rendering rules for
MathML presentation elements</label>
<def><p>Defined throughout <specref ref="presm"/>; the ones that use other
terms defined here occur mainly in <specref ref="presm_mo"/> and in
<specref ref="presm_enliven"/>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-tex">T<sub>E</sub>X</label>

<def><p>A software system developed by Professor Donald Knuth for
typesetting documents.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-token-element">Token element</label>
<def><p>Presentation token element or a Content token element.  (See
above.)</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-toplevel-element">Top-level element (of MathML)</label>
<def><p><el>math</el> (defined in <specref ref="interf_toplevel"/>).</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-typeface">Typeface</label>
<def><p>A typeface is a specific design of a set of letters, numbers and
symbols, such as <quote>Times Roman</quote> or <quote>Chicago</quote>.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-valid-mathml">Valid MathML data</label>
<def><p>MathML data that (1) conforms to the MathML DTD, (2) obeys the
additional rules defined in the MathML standard for the legal contents and
attribute values of each MathML element, and (3) satisfies the EBNF grammar
for content elements.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-width">Width (of a box)</label>
<def><p>The distance from the left edge of the box to the right edge of the
box.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-xsl">Extensible Style Language (XSL)</label>
<def><p>A style language for XML developed by W3C. See XSL FO and XSLT.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-xslfo">XSL Formatting Objects (XSL FO)</label>
<def><p>An XML vocabulary to express formatting, which is a part of XSL.</p></def>
</gitem>

<gitem>
<label id="dt-xslt">XSL Transformation (XSLT)</label>
<def><p>A language to express the transformation of XML documents
into other XML documents.</p></def>
</gitem>
</glist>
</inform-div1>

<!-- LocalWords:  malignmark IEC sep ci cn DSSSL mrow ActiveX mprescripts Pre -->
<!-- LocalWords:  mmultiscripts pre maction FO
-->
